In this video, I'll be discussing loops.
We'll cover basic loops, while loops, and infinite loops.
So when you're writing programs, it's often required to repeat actions in code more than
once, or to iterate over the items in a collection.
And these tests are accomplished by using loops.
In Go, there's only one keyword that we use for looping, and that is the "for" keyword.
Let's take a look at the basic C-style loop.
So we have the "for" keyword, followed by the initialization statement, a condition check,
and the "post loop" statement.
Each one of these portions is separated with semicolons, so you have three sections.
Initialization, condition, and post.
To recreate our loop with the "for" keyword, in our initialization statement, we would
typically create a new variable, and it's usually named "I" for iteration.
Usually you start at zero, but you can start at any point you want.
We're using the Create and Assign operator to create "I" and assign it the value of zero.
Our condition portion of the loop will be checked before every iteration.
So what's going to happen is we'll create this variable "I".
It's then going to be checked to see if it's less than 10.
And then if it is, we're going to enter into this loop.
So then all the code in here will get executed.
Once execution completes, we'll go back up to this "post" statement, and "I" will be
incremented by using the "plus-plus" operator.
"plus-plus" just adds one to "I".
So in the first iteration, "I" will be zero, "I" is less than 10, because it's zero.
The code will execute, then "I" will be incremented by one, and then we'll check again.
So is "I" less than 10, it'll be one at that point, yes it is, and we'll execute.
And this will continue until finally "I" is equal to 10.
Once it's 10, this check will fail, and it'll be false, and then we'll exit out of
the loop, and continue executing code.
Go does support while loops, however, we can only use the "for" keyword in Go, since
there's only one loop in keyword.
So to create a while loop, we'll just use the "for" keyword, and a condition.
Note that the condition must have the variable created beforehand, so "I" needs to
exist prior to using this loop.
If this happens to evaluate the true, then the loop will execute.
One thing to note with this style of looping is you'll always want to adjust the loop
counter within this loop, otherwise it'll just go on forever.
We also have support for infinite loops.
So if we want an infinite loop, we can just use "for", and then nothing else.
All we need is our curly braces right here, and then the code within is just going to execute
over and over and over.
In order to exit an infinite loop, we'll have to use the "break" keyword.
Usually you would check, so in this case we're checking if something happened is true,
then we'll break.
And if it's false, then we'll just keep continuing on forever, since this is an infinite
loop.
Loops like this will be used for something like web servers, or if you're reading data
from some kind of data stream, and then you would choose the condition on which to break.
We also have the "Continue" keyword, which can be used to skip the current loop.
So we have a typical for loop, where we're setting i to 0, as long as it's less than 10,
we're going to loop, and we're incrementing one time each iteration.
Within our loop we have an if statement, and we're checking the i with remainder division
of 2, and if that's equal to 0, we'll continue.
So what this will do is this will skip every iteration where i is an even number.
That means as soon as "Continue" is hit, we'll go straight up here, and we'll do the
condition check again.
So this code will never get executed down here, if the "Continue" is hit first.
However, if we have an odd number, then this will be false, and "Continue" will not
be executed, and therefore we will print out the odd numbers.
Let's recap.
The "For" keyword creates a loop.
We can use the "Break" keyword to exit the loop on a specific condition.
The initialization variable can be used only within the loop block, and the post statement
executes every iteration.
We have three styles of loops, we have the typical loop, where you get to set the variable,
the condition, and how much it changes.
We have the while loop, where we have a variable created previously, and as long as
that variable is less than the value supplied here, then we'll execute the loop.
Always remember to increment that within your loop, otherwise it'll go on forever.
Then we have the intentional infinite loop, where there's nothing right here.
We just have four and our curly braces, and that will just go on forever.